Guide to the Eugene A. Livingston Family Photograph Collection [1855-1887] PR 138
New-York Historical Society
Eugene A. Livingston Family Photograph Collection
[1855-1887]
New-York Historical Society
PR 138
7.41 Linear feet (8 boxes)
Photograph collection primarily consisting of formal studio portraits of members of the family of Eugene A. Livingston, including elaborate frames and photograph albums.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
The family of Eugene Augustus Livingston (1813-1893) comprises one branch of the politically and socially prominent Livingston family of the Hudson Valley and New York City. Eugene A. Livingston, son of Robert L. Livingston (1775-1843) and Margaret Maria Livingston (1783-1818), had seven children. Harriet Coleman Livingston bore him two children: Eugene Livingston (1845-1862), who died in the civil war, and Mary Coleman Livingston Delafield, who became the wife of Maturin L. Delafield. With his second wife, Elizabeth Fisher Livingston, he fathered Adelaide Livingston, Elizabeth Livingston, Katharine Livingston Clymer, Richard M.C. Livingston, and Walter Eugene Livingston. The family lived both in New York City and at their summer home, Teviot, on the Hudson River.
Scope and Content Note
The Eugene A. Livingston Family Photograph Collection spans the period 1855 to 1887 and primarily contains photographic portraits of the Livingston family and their pets. The collection is divided into two series: Loose Photographs; and Albums and Framed Photographs.
Arrangement
Photographs have been arranged in two series:
Missing Title
Series I: Loose Photographs
Series II: Albums and Framed Photographs
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
Documents relating to the family of Eugene A. Livingston are available in the Robert R. Livingston Papers in the Manuscript Department of the New-York Historical Society Library.
Tintypes (prints); Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Fine bindings.; Photograph albums.; Cabinet photographs.; Ambrotypes (photographs); Albumen prints.; Dogs -- Photographs.; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896; Clymer family -- Portraits; Delafield (Family) -- Portraits; Delafield, Maturin L.; Le Gray, Gustave, 1820-1882; Livingston (Family) -- Portraits; Livingston, Adelaide, 1872-1909; Livingston, Elizabeth, 1857-1941; Livingston, Eugene A., 1813-1893; Livingston, Eugene, 1845-1862; Livingston, Goodhue, 1867-1951; Livingston, Richard M. C.; Livingston, Walter Eugene, 1863-; Pach Brothers (Firm)
- Series I: Loose Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I dates from 1870 through 1887 and includes tintypes, albumen prints, cabinet photographs, an ambrotype, and cartes-de-visite. Photographs are filed alphabetically by sitter or subject. Many items are undated. Formal studio portraits by a variety of American and European portrait photographers make up the majority of the collection. Most portraits are of Eugene A. Livingston's children. Also portrayed are Mary Livingston Delafield's husband, Maturin L. Delafield, and children, as well as members of the Clymer family. A few landscapes and group photographs are included. This series also contains several folders of studio portraits of the family's dogs, including portraits by the Pach Brothers. Photographs of several Livingston family paintings include a portrait of Margaret Beekman Livingston. One folder of vintage carte-de-visite size photograph envelopes is filed at the end of the series.
  - Clymer, George, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clymer, Katherine Livingston, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Delafield, Joseph L. (1871-1924) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Delafield, Mary C. Livingston (1847-1922), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Delafield, Maturin L. (1869-1922), 1870-1871 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Group Portraits, 1878, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Landscapes, 1879, 1887, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Livingston, Adelaide, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Livingston, Elizabeth (1857-1941), 1872-1874, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Livingston, Margaret Beekmand (copy photograph of painting), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Livingston, Richard M.C. (silhouette), 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Livingston, Richard M.C. with Walter Eugene, 1870, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Livingston, Robert R. (copy photograph of painting), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Livingston Family Dogs, 1876, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Unidentified Females, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Unidentified Males, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - W. Bienmuller photograph envelopes, cartes-de-visite size, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
- Series II: Albums and Framed Photographs
  Series II dates from circa 1855 through 1885 and includes undated items. Of particular interest and rarity are several elaborate frames including one leather, easel-mounted, fold-out book frame; one frame featuring a hand-painted silk mat; and two velvet frames. Also present is a glass stereograph view of the family's Hudson Valley summer home, Teviot (formerly known as Eversleigh). Seven albums ranging in size from 4 3/4 x 3 1/2 inches to 11 x 9 1/4 inches make up the bulk of this series. One cartes-de-visite album has a wooden cover with a carved stag's head protruding from the front; the smallest of the albums portrays a female figure in inlayed wood. Some allegorical tableaus are included in the scrapbooks.
  Portrait photographs by several prominent photographers is also included; a portrait of Eugene A. Livingston and his two eldest children, Mary and Eugene Livingston (1845-1862), taken and signed by Gustave Le Gray is included in its original housing, as are carte-de-visite portraits by Mathew Brady. A framed portrait of a print of General Philip H. Sheridan is identified on the verso as "possibly" being Sheridan; a comparison with portraits at different ages indicates that it is very likely Sheridan.
  - Album of family portraits, a few published views of European and domestic landmarks, and dog portraits, [1877]; 9 1/2 x 8 1/2 (Offsite-box 3)
  - Album of cartes-de-visite and cabinet cards portraying Livingston family members and family dogs, [1867-1880]; 9 x 11 in. (Offsite-box 4)
  - Tintype of Adelaide, Elizabeth, and Katherine Livingston, 1864 (Offsite-box 5)
  - Album of cartes-de-visite with leather and wooden cover portraying female figure in inlaid wood, undated; 4 3/4 x 3 1/2 in. (Offsite-box 5)
  - Album of cartes-de-visite and tintypes, primarily of Livingston family members; includes allegorical tableaus., 1871-1884, undated; 5 1/2 x 4 1/4 in. (Offsite-box 5)
  - Album of cartes-de-visite and tintypes, includes portraits by Mathew Brady, [1860-1870]; 6 1/2 x 5 3/4 in. (Offsite-box 5)
  - Album of cartes-de-visite portraits and copy photographs of paintings, undated; 6 1/2 x 6 in. (Offsite-box 5)
  - Black leather easel-mounted, book-style, fold-out frame with 29 cabinet cards and carte-de-visite portraits, [1865-1885] (Offsite-box 6)
  - Album with wooden cover, a carved stag's head protrudes from the front, holding cartes-de-visite primarily of Livingston family members, [1869-1871]; 5 x 3 3/4 in. (Offsite-box 6)
  - Glass stereoscopic view of Teviot (house), [1861-1869] (Offsite-box 7)
  - Fold-out canvas frame with four cabinet card portraits of Livingston family members, [1886] (Offsite-box 7)
  - Leather frame with two cabinet card portraits of K. McL.L. and W.B.S. Clymer, 1882, undated (Offsite-box 7)
  - Leather frame with two cabinet card portraits of Katherine Livingston Clymer and two unidentified women, 1882, 1885 (Offsite-box 7)
  - Glass-covered cabinet card portrait of Maturin Livingston Delafield, undated (Offsite-box 7)
  - Glass-covered print of General Philip Sheridan, undated (Offsite-box 7)
  - Glass-covered portrait of Eugene A. Livingston, Mary C. Livingston, and Eugene Livingston, Jr. taken and signed by Gustave Le Gray, Paris, [1855] (Offsite-box 7)
  - Ambrotype of an unidentified young man, 1857 Jan. 17 (Offsite-box 8)
  - Portrait of an unidentified man, possibly Eugene A. Livingston, in a small metal easel frame, undated (Offsite-box 8)
  - Frame with hand-painted silk mat holding a cartes-de-visite portrait of an unidentified woman, undated (Offsite-box 8)
  - Green velvet fold-out frame with 6 cabinet card portraits, 1876-1879 (Offsite-box 8)
  - Turquoise velvet fold-out frame with 6 cabinet card portraits, 1877-1881 (Offsite-box 8)